<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament; straightly charging and forbidding all in-keepers, victuallers, alehouse-keepers, or other persons whatsoever, to harbour or entertain any marriners, sea-men, water-men, &amp;c. prest into any of His Majesties or merchants ships employed in this service after the beat of the drum, and proclamation made to give them notice, to repair on boord the severall ships to which they belong. Ordered by the Lords and Commoms in Parliament, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com. Also a letter from Sir Iohn Hotham. Ordered by Commons in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1459A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E95_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E95[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament; straightly charging and forbidding all in-keepers, victuallers, alehouse-keepers, or other persons whatsoever, to harbour or entertain any marriners, sea-men, water-men, &amp;c. prest into any of His Majesties or merchants ships employed in this service after the beat of the drum, and proclamation made to give them notice, to repair on boord the severall ships to which they belong. Ordered by the Lords and Commoms in Parliament, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com. Also a letter from Sir Iohn Hotham. Ordered by Commons in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Husbands, and are to be sold at his shop in the middle Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Aprill 7. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In place of Hotham's letter announcing the desertion of Sir Hugh Cholmley to the King are given the Commons' actions upon receipt of the news, which were separately printed as a broadside with caption : Die lunae, 3 April, 1643.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: Text on reel is stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
            <p>A DECLARATION <hi>Of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in</hi> PARLIAMENT; Straightly charging and forbidding all In-Keepers, Victuallers, Alehouſe-keepers, or other perſons whatſoever, to harbour or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any Marriners, Sea-men, Water-men, &amp;c. Preſt into any of His Majeſties or Merchants Ships employed in this ſervice after the beat of the Drum, and Proclamation made to give them notice, to repair on Boord the ſeveral Ships to which they belong.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Ordered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, That this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a Letter from Sir IOHN HOTHAM.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, That this Letter be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Husbands,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the middle Temple. Aprill 7. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Parliamentary_declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:111617:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111617:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there are ſeverall Fleets now ſetting forth to the Seas, under the command of the Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this Kingdom, and the reſt of His Majeſties Dominions in this time of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger, which will be much retarded, if all effectuall means be not uſed for the providing them with able Marriners and Sea-men, Water-men, &amp;c. The Lords and Commons in Parliament doe hereby ſtraightly charge and forbid all Inkeepers, Victuallers, Alehouſekeepers, or other perſons whatſoever, to harbour, or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Marriners, Sea-men, Water-men, &amp;c. Preſt into any of His Majeſties, or Merchants Ships employed in this ſervice after the beate of the Drum, and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation made, to give them notice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111617:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->on Boord the ſeverall Ships to which they belong; And in caſe any Inkeep<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, Victualler, Alehouſekeeper, or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhall be found faulty herein; The ſaid Lords and Commons doe declare, That they will not only proceed ſeverally againſt all ſuch for their contempt, but cauſe their Licenſes for Inne, or Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers to be made voyd, and themſelves diſ-enabled hereafter from ſuch employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And do further require the principal Officers &amp; Commiſsioners of the Navie, to ſuffer no payments to be made of ſuch debts as ſhall be contracted by Marriners, Saylers, or Water-men in any Victualling houſe, Alehouſe, Inne, or the like as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, out of the wages due to any ſuch Marriners, Saylers, or Water-men.</p>
            <p>Except it be to ſuch houſe-keepers as doe receive any of the ſaid Marriners or Sea-men into their houſes being ſick or ſet on ſhore for the recovery of their health, and ſuch Inkeepers, Alehouſekeepers, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuallers, or others, as ſhall ſo receive or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111617:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->entertain any of the ſaid Sea-men, are to have a teſtimony in writing, under the hand of the Lord Generall the Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> or the Captain of the ſhip, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of two of the chief Officers of the ſaid ſhip, from whence the ſick man comes.</p>
            <p>And the Lords and Commons do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declare, That if any Marriner, Sayler, Water-men, &amp;c. after his receiving of preſt and conduct money, neglect to make his appearance according to the time limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Ticket, or ſhall preſume to run away, or deſert the ſaid ſervice, in this time of eminent and publick danger, that all ſuch perſons ſo apprehended, ſhall bee proceeded againſt by the E: of <hi>Warwick,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome and rules of War, in that behalfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:111617:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Luna, 3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> April, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Letter from Sir <hi>Iohn Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi> from Hull, of the firſt of this April inſtant, expreſsing Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmleys</hi> deſerting the Parliament, and the regaining of Searborough by his directions, by the courage and induſtry of Captain <hi>Buſhell;</hi> and his deſires that Captain <hi>Buſhell</hi> might have the command of that place, by his nomination, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Commands and Orders
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111617:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->from him, was this day Read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved upon the queſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <lb/>
That Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> bee forthwith diſabled for continuing any longer a Member of this Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved upon the queſtion.</hi>
               <lb/>
That Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> ſhall be for ever diſabled for ſitting as a Member of Parliament in this Houſe, for falſly and perfidiouſly betraying the truſt repoſed in him by the Parliament, falſifying his Proteſtation, and revolting to the Popiſh Army raiſed againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:111617:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111617:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111617:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved upon the queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> ſhall be impeached of High Treaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Marten,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Peter Wentworth,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henry Hayman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Samuel Browne,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. Sergeant <hi>Wilde,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter Solicitor,</item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Rous,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Strode,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Are appointed to prepare an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of High-treaſon againſt Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge Cler. Parl. D.C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
